NYSUT Division of Research and Educational Services Files. 6174/003
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- Conference – Human Relations, Syracuse See also: Human Relations, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  November 30, 1973, Work sheets for communications exercises at statewide human relations conferences; list of registrants.
- Conference – Human Relations, Buffalo, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  Agenda, exercise materials
- Conference – North Babylon Teachers Conference, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  Agenda; letter to NYSUT research director Charles Santelli confirming his scheduled address to the conference
- Conference – Northeast Research Directors, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  Agenda; summary of 1970 Census Data Available for School Districts
- Conference – Pennsylvania State Education Association (PSEA) Meeting, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  September 11, 1973. Call for Mid-Eastern Regional Research meeting, with list of topics
- Conference – Rocky Point Public Schools Conference, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  Program for Professional Conference Day, remarks of Daniel Klepak, director, State Office of November 15, 1973. Education Performance Review, at the 54th Convention of the New York State School Boards Association, re deficiencies in public education system, October 28, 1973; State Education Department report, "The Pupil Evaluation Program: Statewide Report October 1992 Reading and Mathematics Test Results," August 1993; newspaper clippings; handwritten notes
- Conference – Riverhead Workshop – Salaries (folder 1) See also: Financial - Miscellaneous, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  Tentative agenda; NYSTA Research and Information Services 1971-72 brochure; NYSTA Research document, Jericho Regional Office Area 1971-72 Salary Schedule Summary for Teachers; NYSTA Research Memorandum, Summary of 1971-72 Agreement Provisions: Jericho january 28, 1972.Regional Area; NYSTA Information Services Memorandum, Personal Income in New York State, September 1971; Estimated Net Effective Buying Income and Net Cash Income of Households, September 1971; Salaries of Inexperienced College Graduates: How Do Teachers' Salaries Compare with Other Fields? (male and female teachers excluding NYC vs male college graduates including NYC), November 1971; NYSTA Research memorandum supplement, Preliminary Analysis of 1972 Endicott Survey, January 27, 1972; Cost of Living Trends, January 24, 1972; Right of Access to Data, re right of taxpayers to examine school district records, January 1972; NYSTA Research memorandum, Selected 1970-71 Financial Data for School Districts: Nassau-Suffolk Counties, January 1972
- Conference – Riverhead Workshop – Salary Statistics (folder 2), 1971-1974 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  Statistical research documents: 1971-72 Salary Schedules and Selected Agreement Provisions, Associated Community College Facilities NYSTA; Teacher Salaries and Salary Schedules 1973-1974, and Selected Salary Data for School Administrators, January 1974
- Conference – Riverhead Workshop – Salary Statistics (folder 3), 1971-1972 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  California Agency for Research in Education; National Education Association Research Division reports re Salaries Paid and Salary-Related Practices in Higher Education, 1971-72
- Conference – Rome Teachers Association In-Service, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  April 6, 1973. Agenda
- Conference – Workshops (Educational Technology) 1973 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  List of workshops for second annual educational technology conference
- Conference – Workshop (Finance), 1970 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  December 12, 1970. Agenda; worksheets for analysis of district budgets and annual financial reports
- Conference – Workshops, 1971-1972 (Box 9, Folder 21)
  Routine correspondence re assorted workshops
- Conference – Teacher Education, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 22)
  March 24-28, 1972. Position papers, reports, correspondence
- Conference – Teacher Education, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 23)
  August 10-11, 1972. NYSTA program; materials re competency-based certification
- Conference – Performance-Based Teacher Education, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 24)
  March 12, 1973. Program
- Albany PTSA, 1995 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  May 16, 1995. Handwritten notes
- Carmel, 1995 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  March 24, 1995. Draft of NYSUT president Tom Hobart's convention speech; list of Carmel teachers salaries; letter from NYS Republican Committee, urging pressure on Assemblyman Pordum to support Gov. Pataki's proposed "workfare" legislation; transcript of Republican television ad; handwritten notes
- Long Island President's Conference, 1995 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  February 10-11, 1995. Application for Twenty-First Century Schools program, which would exempt schools from many regulations and laws; statement of Thomas Sobol, announcing resignation as Commissioner of Education; text of proposed budget legislation and discussion paper
- E.D. #13 Meeting, 1994 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  January 12, 1994. NYSUT Division of Research and Educational Services monthly report
- E.D. (Election District) Meeting, 1986 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  February 8, 1986. Packet of newspaper clippings and other materials for NYSUT Regional Leadership Conference, "Union Leadership on Professional Issues," February 8, 1986; handwritten notes
- Fulton-Montgomery Cluster, 1986 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  August 23, 1986. Meeting announcement, handwritten note
- Lindenhurst Conference, 1986 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  January 4, 1986. Handwritten notes
- North Babylon Teachers Organization, 1986 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  November 4, 1986. Agenda for conference; letter to NYSUT vice president Antonia Cortese asking her to give a presentation re teacher centers
- Workshops (folder 1), 1983-1985 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  NYSUT publications: Part 100 of Commissioner's Regulations, August 15, 1985; Guide to Implementation of Part 100 of Commissioner's Regulations, April 26 (prepared for the 1985 NYSUT Representative Assembly); Vocational Education Futuring Alert materials, February 1982; Selected Financial Data: Districts in the NYSUT Western New York Area: Negotiations Workshop, November 22-23, 1985; U.S. Department of Education national invitational conference, February 25-27, 1982, paper: "Research on Teaching: Implications for Practice," "Recruitment, Selection and Retention: The Shape of the Teaching Force"; NYSUT packet of press releases of July action of Board of Regents, sent to regional coordinators, August 3, 1983
- Workshops (folder 2), 1984 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  AFL-CIO Public Employee Department publication, "In Search of the Reagan Tax Cut: Update 1984"; report by Public Policy Institute and NYS Job Training Partnership Council, "The Impact of Migration on New York State: Summary of Findings," September 1984; NY State Education Department draft document for discussion only, "Revised Proposed New Part 100 of the Commissioner's Regulations, " September 21, 1984; NYSUT discussion paper on Board of Regents' Proposed Action Plan to Improve Elementary and Secondary Education, January 1984; testimony of Antonia Cortese, second vice president, NYSUT, to the Board of Regents on the Regents Legislative Proposals, September 19, 1984
- Workshops (folder 3), 1981-1985 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  Memos, handwritten notes
- Consultant Fees, 1981-1989 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  Memos recommending higher fees for consultants used by NYSUT for conferences and workshops; related correspondence
- Consultant Teacher, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  NYSUT Information Bulletin re consultant teacher services
- Contingency Budgets, 1972-1977 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  Memos from NY State Education Department discussing austerity budgets; NYSUT memo and background paper re how contingency budgets are determined and adopted following repeated rejection by voters
- Contract Analysis (folder 1), 1976-1979 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  Weekly contract summaries for public school districts, community colleges, and BOCES; related memos
- Contract Analysis (folder 2), 1976-1979 (Box 10, Folder 16)
- Copyright, 1983-1987 (Box 10, Folder 17)
  NYSUT memorandum, "Copyright Guidelines and Educational 'Fair Use' for Educators," n.d.; related correspondence
- Corporal Punishment 1984-1985 (Box 10, Folder 18)
  NYSUT Background Paper for Regents' Discussion of Corporal Punishment, primarily re assaults on teachers by students, November 27, 1984; memo from NYSUT general counsel discussing legal grounds for corporal punishment, including Biblical basis for common law presumption, and state and U.S. Supreme Court cases upholding corporal punishment as means of asserting school authority, January 29, 1985; correspondence re reporting requirements; memo to Regents from Education Commission Gordon Ambach noting that SED counsel had advised that they do not have the authority to ban corporal punishment, November 19, 1984
- Corporal Punishment 1979-1987 (Box 10, Folder 19)
  Children Magazine's Report Card on Corporal Punishment in America's Schools, Rodale Press; amendments to Rules of the Board of Regents, prohibiting corporal punishment; legal opinions by NYSUT general counsel; handwritten notes; newspaper clippings
- Cost of Education, 1980 (Box 10, Folder 20)
  c.1980. NYSUT bulletin making statistical argument that the cost of education is low compared with other state and local government expenditures, inflation, personal income, etc.
- Counseling See: Guidance
- Cuomo, Mario (Governor), 1990 (Box 10, Folder 21)
  Message to the Legislature, January 3, 1990; "1989 State of the Union Address," unattributed (probably not Cuomo) speech to NYSUT Representative Assembly
- Curriculum Mandates (folder 1) See also: Task Force on the Hurried Child See also: Academic Standards, 1976-1977 (Box 10, Folder 22)
  NYSUT report, "Curriculum Mandates," 1977; State Education Department study papers; NYSUT policy statements; correspondence.
- Curriculum Mandates (folder 2), 1976-1977 (Box 10, Folder 23)
  Correspondence
- Data Processing Needs Assessment See also: Computer Committee, 1988 (Box 10, Folder 24)
  Correspondence re computer software and equipment issues, including updating data files.
- Declining Enrollments, 1980 (Box 10, Folder 25)
  Charts and graphs re national enrollment trends; NYSUT memo re alternatives to teacher layoffs in response to declining enrolment, December 18, 1980; fact sheet, the Impact of Declining Enrollment; handwritten notes
- Developmental Disabilities and Infant Mortality Prevention See also: Handicapped See also: Handicapping See also: Special Education, 1981 (Box 10, Folder 26)
  Letter from NYSUT president Tom Hobart to the Governor's Conference for the Prevention of Developmental Disabilities and Infant Mortality, questioning recommendation to mandate K-12 sex education, access to services by pre-school handicapped children, July 22, 1981.
- Disabilities – Autism and Lovaas See also: Handicapped See also: Handicapping See also: Special Education, 1996 (Box 10, Folder 27)
  Seminar paper, "Lovaas, TEACCH, And the Public System: The Court as Referee," by Myrna Mandlawitz, National Association of State Directors of Special Education (NASDSE); summaries of legal cases; article reprints.
- Disabilities – Awarding High School Credit to Disabled See also: Handicapped See also: Handicapping See also: Special Education, 1996 (Box 10, Folder 28)
  Confidential memo from NYSUT associate Phil Ellis re State Education Department draft memo re high school course credit for students with disabilities, May 31, 1996; text of SED draft memo, June 1996; memo to Regents "for emergency action" to allow more flexibility under Commissioner's Regulations for assigning a teacher to teach a subject without certification in the subject, May 24, 1996; NY State Education Department Office of Vocational and Educational Services for Individuals with Disabilities: Report on Disability Issues, June 1996; spreadsheet showing numbers of students receiving special education services in New York State, by type of disability and age, December 1992-94.
- Disabilities – Effective Practices for Inclusive Programs See also: Handicapped See also: Handicapping See also: Special Education, 1992-1994 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  c. 1992-1994. Technical assistance planning guide prepared by California Research Institute (San Francisco State University) and U.S. Department of Education (not officially endorsed), n.d., c. 1992; cover letter to Phil Ellis from U.S. Department of Education, August 4, 1994.
- Disabilities – IDELR Highlights (Individuals with Disabilities Education Law Report) See also: Handicapped See also: Handicapping See also: Special Education, 1994-1995 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  Newsletters.
- Disaggregation, 1990 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  State Education Department Advisory Committee on Disaggregation meeting minutes, re tagging individual students with permanent socioeconomic (?) status identifiers for a central database (contains acronyms never spelled out), August 17, 1990
- Distance Learning, 1987-1988 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  Report by NYS Legislative Commission on Science and Technology, "Distance Learning: The Sky's the Limit," September 1988; "Survey of Distance Learning Projects: A Report to the NYSUT Task Force on Educational Technology," May 1987; draft report for discussion only, "SUNYSAT Distance Education Interest Survey" Executive Summary, January 1990; correspondence re legislative proposals
- Donovan Plan, 1985-1986 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  Testimony of Thomas Y. Hobart, president, NYSUT, at the NYS Senate Education Committee Hearing on Strengthening Teaching in Elementary and Secondary Schools, January 28, 1986; edited draft; letter from Senate Education Committee chair James H. Donovan inviting Hobart to testify, with attached committee report, "Teacher Improvement Program: The Third Year," December 24, 1985; Education Week article re education reform in New Jersey, n.d., press release from Assembly Speaker's office, "Fink Issues Mid-Term Report Card on Education Task Force Goals," December 27, 1985
- Donovan Commission Testimony, 1985 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  "T.I.P.: Teacher Improvement Program: The Third Year; Report from the Senate Education Committee, James H. Donovan, chairman," December 1985, with cover letter from Donovan to NYSUT president Hobart; unsigned testimony (probably by Hobart) at Donovan hearings, January 14, 1986; handwritten memo to Hobart from Pat Flynn critiquing testimony, January 8, 1986; press release by Assembly Speaker Stanley Fink, report card on education task force goals, December 27, 1985
- Donovan Testimony, 1986 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  Drafts of testimony by NYSUT president Thomas Hobart to the Senate Education Committee (Sen. Donovan, chair) hearing on Strengthening Teaching in Elementary and Secondary Schools, January 28, 1986
- Dropouts – Skills Opportunity Centers See also: Attendance See also: Regan/Ambach/Hobart – SED Audit, 1991 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  Briefing paper; memo to NYSUT president Tom Hobart from governor's office seeking comment on proposed legislation establishing and funding BOCES-administered centers for dropouts, March 20, 1991; reply from Hobart, stating opposition, April 12, 1991; comments from other NYSUT officials.
- Dutchess United Educators Meeting See also: Certification – Dutchess County Teachers Council, 1986 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  December 10, 1986. NYSUT report, "Data Relative to New York State Community Colleges under SUNY Jurisdiction: Revenues & Expenditures for 1982-83," February 1986; lists of contract expiration dates for various community colleges.
- Dyson and Nyquist, 1976 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  Newspaper clippings re calls by Board of Regents for resignation of Education Commissioner Ewald Nyquist over racial integration, accountability, and other issues, criticism by Commerce Commissioner John S. Dyson and Gov. Hugh Carey; NYSUT memo re audit of NYC Bureau of Child Guidance, with reference to Dyson comments, October 4, 1976
- Early Childhood (folder 1), 1995 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  Reports: Child Care Capital Construction Preliminary Report, prepared by NYS Department of Social Services, February 1995; NYS Child Care Coordinating Council 1995 Child Care Agenda; Evaluation of the Collaborative Child Care Demonstration Project, final report, December 1994; fact sheet by U.S. Department of Health and Human Services Administration for Children and Families re child care programs, January 1995; Statement of Thomas Sobol, Commissioner of Education, before the NYS Senate Finance and Assembly Ways and Means Committees, February 8, 1995; letter to NYS Gov. Pataki from Advisory Committee on Early Childhood Programs, outlining recommendations for streamlining child care services in New York, January 27, 1995; press releases from Government Watch '95 (human services provider advocacy group) criticizing governor's budget cuts and stricter regulations for child care and other welfare supports, February 8 and 10, 1995; agenda and handwritten notes of early childhood meeting, 2/17/95
- Early Childhood (folder 2), 1994 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  Preliminary report, proceedings of the "Vision 21" Education Symposium, January 12-14, 1994, "New York's K-12 Public Education in the 21st Century: A Framework for Action," sponsored by the Legislative Commission on Rural Resources; report by New York State Permanent Interagency Committee on Early Childhood Program, "Comprehensive Career Development Plan: Issues, Background Statements, and Objectives," April 1994, with cover letter soliciting comments; compilation of comments, June 15; follow-up questionnaire, September 14; related memos
- Early Childhood (folder 3), 1993-1994 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  "Putting Children First," vol. 1, by NYS Special Commission on Educational Structure, Policies and Practices, December 1993; "Comprehensive Services in Early Childhood Programs: Preliminary Results of Survey to Assess Needs and Improve Services for Children and Families," NYS Council on Children and Families, November 1994; "Changing a Generation's Destiny: Restructuring Services for New York's High Risk and Troubled Children," State Communities Association, recommending replacing NYS Council on Children and Families with NYS Department for Children and Families, noting deterioration of services since 1991 report, c. 1994; text of governor's program bill to amend the education law to coordinate school and community services, 1994
- Early Childhood (folder 4), 1992-1994 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  Testimony of Antonia Cortese, first vp, NYSUT, to the Board of Regents and NYS Education Department on Supporting Young Children and Families: A Proposed Regents Policy Statement on Early Childhood, September 30, 1992; testimony by Cortese to Regents and SED at their 1995 Legislative Conference, September 21, 1994; NYSUT comments on Comprehensive Early Childhood Center Development Initiative; materials for December 19, 1994, meeting of Advisory Committee to the Permanent Interagency Committee on Early Childhood Programs, including summary of September 9, 1994, meeting, handwritten notes, and draft report recommending interagency coordination
- Early Childhood (folder 5), 1993-1994 (Box 11, Folder 15)
  Draft guidelines from NYS Department of Social Services and NYS Department of Health, "Promoting Children's Health in Early Childhood Programs: Guidelines and Technical Assistance for Caregivers," with cover letter soliciting comments, September 9, 1994; correspondence re NYS Comprehensive Early Childhood Career Development Initiative; "Supporting Young Children and Families: A Regents Policy Statement on Early Childhood," with background paper and draft action plan for implementation, June 1993
- Early Childhood (folder 6), 1993-1994 (Box 11, Folder 16)
  U.S. Department of Education National Center for Education Statistics report, "Student Data Handbook for Early Childhood, Elementary, and Secondary Education"; NYSUT memo "noting our concerns" re proposal to open state pre-K expansion funds to child care providers, April 1, 1993; handwritten notes
- Early Childhood – PICECP Meeting, 1994 (Box 11, Folder 17)
  September 9, 1994. Third draft of final report, "Evaluation of the Collaborative Child Care Demonstration Project," prepared for Permanent Interagency Committee on Early Childhood Programs (PICECP), requesting comments, August 17, 1994; memo to the Collaborative Structures Subcommittee of PICECP requesting comments on third final draft, August 17, 1994; Carnegie Corporation report, "Starting Points: Meeting the Needs of Our Youngest Children" (abridged version), August 1994; draft report, "Preparing Our Children for the Next Century: An Early Childhood Action Plan for New York State," August 30, 1994; handwritten notes
- Early Childhood – PICECP Advisory Committee, 1994 (Box 11, Folder 18)
  May 16, 1994. Meeting notices; minutes; focus group questions; handwritten notes
- Early Childhood – PICECP Collaborative Structures, 1994 (Box 11, Folder 19)
  April 25, 1994. Agenda for April 25 meeting; summary of meeting; draft report, "Head Start and Child Care in New York State," prepared by Early Childhood Policy Research, for the NYS Department of Social Services Bureau of Early Childhood Services, c. 1993; report, "Day Care Collaborative Demonstration Program Highlights of Preliminary Findings from Site Visits," April 25. 1994; prospectus, "The Finance Project: Toward Improved Ways and Means of Financing Education and Other Children's Services," October 1993; handwritten notes
- Early Childhood – PICECP Collaborative Structures (NYSUT Opposition to Multi-Funded Projects), 1988-1993 (Box 11, Folder 20)
  Draft recommendations of Collaborative Structures Subcommittee: Promoting Multi-Funded Early Childhood Programs, January 6, 1993; letter from Santelli to Council on Children and Families summarizing NYSUT policy statements on early childhood services and programs, insisting that all funds be given to public schools, October 18, 1988; related correspondence
- Early Childhood – PICECP Collaborative Structures Subcommittee, 1993 (Box 11, Folder 21)
  October, 1, 1993. Meeting agenda; letter from NYSUT president Hobart to Foundation for Child Development reiterating NYSUT's minority opinion that no funds should given over to "the underprepared direction of a daycare center director," June 24, 1993; report by subcommittee, "Promoting Multi-Funded Early Childhood Programs," revised May 17, 1993
- Early Childhood – PICECP Collaborative Structures Subcommittee, 1994 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  January 10, 1994. Summaries of January 10, 1994, and October 1, 1993, meetings; discussion item for Regents: progress report on implementation of the Regents Early Childhood Policy Statement, December 9, 1993; handwritten notes
- Early Childhood – PICECP Advisory Committee, 1994 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  January 24, 1994. Meeting agenda; Summary of the Findings of the Data Development Work Group, January 1994; executive summary of report on Head Start quality and expansion; handwritten notes
- Early Childhood – PICECP Advisory Committee, 1993 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  Summary of October 5 meeting, with notes about the Morelan Commission, the PICECP Career October 5, 1993. Development Work Group, and a request for a meeting with Hobart or Cortese re early childhood certification; agenda for meeting of October 5, with background materials including "Child Care for Mildly Ill Children, Severity Level One," "Child Care for Moderately Ill Children, Severity Levels Two and Three," "Findings of the Committee on Child Care for Ill Children: Proposal for a System of Child Care for Ill Children in New York," text of Assembly bill re day care services, description of "seamless funding bill"; fact sheet, "Seamless Funding of Child Care Subsidies (A6516-A/S5111-A): Myths and Facts"
- Early Childhood Investment Fund Policy Board, 1993-1994 (Box 12, Folder 4)